בוקר טוב Boker Tov today's דף daf is י"ד Yud Dalet and
we pick up
with אלא אמר מר זוטרא Ella Amar Mar Zutra it's like six
lines in. Basically we're dealing with the משנה mishna that said that
if somebody appoints somebody to deliver a גט get or a שטר
שחרור shtar shichrur to his slave and dies it's not delivered after
he's dead. But if somebody gives away money and he dies commands
that the property be distributed and he dies it is given after
his death and the question is why? So there are basically two
explanations of the משנה mishna one is he said it on his
deathbed and it's based on the principle of דברי שכיב מרע ככתובן
וכמסורן דמו Dibre Shachiv Mera KeKesuvon UkeMesuran Damu words of a שכיב
מרע shachiv mera are like they're signed and sealed and delivered which
basically is חז"ל Chazal you know creating the power for like a
deathbed bequest. And the other explanation is no he's alive and healthy
but all three parties are in the room and it's a principle
of מעמד שלשתן. Maamad Shloshtan. Three parties meaning he's not just saying
give a hundred dollars to ראובן Ruven he's saying the hundred dollars
that שמעון Shimon owes me rather that שמעון Shimon shouldn't pay me
he should pay that hundred dollars to ראובן. Ruven. And שמעון Shimon
and ראובן Ruven are both in the room together with him at
the same time it works and that's a principle called מעמד שלשתן
Maamad Shloshtan the three of them are present. And the גמרא Gemara
wanted to understand what that was based on. If there actually we're
talking about a concrete object that שמעון Shimon is holding onto and
it's being transferred to ראובן Ruven then you know it could work
because it's in שמעון's Shimon property and that's property in a sense
he takes possession of it for ראובן. Ruven. But if it applies
even to an abstract debt not only to a פקדון pikadon but
even a מלוה milve what is the way in which it what
is the way in which it can transfer? So the גמרא Gemara
gave some possible mechanics but it rejected them for various reasons and
the question is how what is the mechanism through which this money
that's owed can be transferred to a third party if they're all
present in the room at the same time? And the גמרא Gemara
says אלא אמר מר זוטרא Ella Amar Mar Zutra so says מר
זוטרא Mar Zutra י"ד עמוד א' Yud Dalet Amud Aleph about six
lines in says מר זוטרא Mar Zutra הני תלת מילי Hani Tlat
Mili these three these three ideas or things שווינהו רבנן
כהלכתא בלא טעמא Shavyinu Rabanan KeHilchata Belo Taama the Rabbis made them
like הלכות halachos without a reason. Now תוספות Tosafot says it doesn't
mean that there's no reason for instituting them it means the mechanics
don't really work. Okay there's no good explanation for the mechanism but
nevertheless the Rabbis said that they'll work even without a clear mechanism.
Okay and what are those three?
וחדא הא Vachada Ha one what we just said the idea of
מעמד שלשתן. Maamad Shloshtan. ואידך Ve'idach the second one is דאמר רב
יהודה אמר שמואל הכותב כל נכסיו לאשתו De'amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel
HaKosev Kol Nechasav LeIshto if somebody writes all of his property into
his wife's name he basically writes a שטר shtar and says he's
giving all of his property to his wife so we say לא
עשאה אלא אפוטרופא Lo Asah Ella Apitropia
he didn't literally transfer it all to his wife it was really
his way of saying that he is empowering her you know to
as the executor. I mean he's not dead but you know as
the person power of attorney he's giving her the authority to make
decisions about the property. Okay but he is not actually transferring its
ownership to him to her. And that's really you know again there's
no good logic it's a שטר shtar maybe he did want to
give it all over why should we interpret it as anything other
than it is? But nevertheless we say no we're going to assume
that logically a person would not give away the way the תוספות
Tosafot we'll read תוספות Tosafot let's look at תוספות Tosafot כהלכתא בלא
טעמא. KeHilchata Belo Taama. תוספות Tosafot says פירוש Peirush מה שמועיל לקנות
Ma SheMoil Liknot meaning what enables it to work it doesn't mean
that there's no purpose for instituting this. The question is what's the
mechanism? The mechanism is not really is not really clear. אבל טעם
יש למה תיקנו חכמים מעמד שלשתן Aval Taam Yesh Lama Tiknu Chachamim
Maamad Shloshtan there's a reason why they instituted the idea the ability
to transfer you know a debt to a third party if they're
all
present. מעמד שלשתן תיקנו Maamad Shloshtan Tiknu מעמד שלשתן Maamad Shloshtan they
did שלא יצטרך לטרוח ולעשות קניינים Shelo Yitzatarech Litroach Velaasot Kinyanim meaning
no because that's an easy and efficient way of transferring you know
property that's owned to me to a third party so I mean
the mechanism isn't clear but you
know it was something that was helpful in the world of commerce
to have the ability to do that. ובהכותב נכסיו לאשתו UveHaKosev Nechasav
LeIshto משום דלא שביק לבריה ויהיב לאחריני Mishum Dela Shavik Livrei Veyahiv
Leachrini the logic is is that we assume that a person would
not want to abandon his children basically write them completely out of
his estate and give all of his property to his wife. Okay
didn't know about our you know survivor laws where it all goes
to the spouse you know in that in those in that world
you know you want to leave your property to your descendants not
to your spouse. So if you're giving it all to your wife
we assume you didn't really mean it. Okay ואין דרך לעשות כן
אלא לחלק לה כבוד ולשויה אפוטרופא Veen Derech Laasot Ken Ella Lachalek
Lah Kavod Velashavya Apitropia the only reason to do it is a
way of saying that you're giving her basically power of attorney. So
actually I mean you can't really explain that he gave it all
over so it's not a clear. it's not so overwhelming that that's
the idea that we would void the gift, but nevertheless we're going
to interpret it through that lens, okay? תו אידך, To idach, back
to the גמרא. Gemara. And the third one is, oh boy, דאמר
רב Rav חנינא המשיא אשה לבנו גדול בבית קנאו. If you basically
marry off your son and you throw a wedding party to him
and you have the חופה chuppah in a house that you built
specifically for your son, not the house that you're living in. תוספות
Tosafot says, or let's say you know, you took all of your
own חפצים chafatzim out of the house and you made the whole
and you sort of had the party in the house and you
know it was just made for him, the house. So in that
case, you basically are assumed to be transferring ownership of the house
to the son. Okay, so those are three things. Now the last
two it's sort of like we are trying to get at your
דעת da'at and we assume that that was your דעת da'at even
though you didn't actually do those things, we use what we presume
your דעת da'at to be to interpret it. The first one, it
was, you know, your דעת da'at is explicit, what's the problem is
that there's not a clear mechanism to transfer, but nevertheless these are
three things that the Rabbis said, these are how the way these
things are going to work, even though the mechanism maybe is not
totally clear. Okay, but that's the principle about מעמד שלשתן ma'amad shloshtan
and then תוספות Tosafot wants to know, once מעמד שלשתן ma'amad shloshtan
works in a somewhat arbitrary way without trying to argue like a
logical mechanism, would it work even if one of the parties, you
know, one of the parties is refusing? If ראובן Reuven owes me
a hundred dollars and I'm saying don't pay me, pay שמעון Shimon
and we're all, me, ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon are all in
the room, what if ראובן Reuven says no, I refuse to transfer
the debt to שמעון? Shimon? So תוספות Tosafot says maybe it doesn't
work because, you know, we don't need a mechanism that makes ראובן
Reuven willing to transfer the money, just חז"ל Chazal gave me the
ability to do that. And then תוספות Tosafot wants to know what
happens if one of the three parties is not Jewish, would it
even work in that case? And תוספות Tosafot speculates about what the
הלכה halacha would be in those scenarios. Okay. So now the גמרא
Gemara says like this. So that's the idea that מעמד שלשתן ma'amad
shloshtan and that might be what's going on in the משנה, Mishnah,
that the guy was healthy and the reason that you give it
לאחר מיתה le'achar mita is because he has this ability to transfer
if all three parties are in the room. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like
this. אמר ליה רב לרב אחא ברדלא Amar lei Rav l'Rav Acha
Bardla קבא דמוריקא, kava de'morika, a קב kav of מוריקא, morika, which
is some type of I think it's some type of a spice
or something,
hold on let me see what... saffron, that's right. So it's a
certain like
huge amount of saffron.
In fact actually especially because saffron was extremely expensive, right?
It costs as much by weight as gold.
Really? Even today?
Even today, yeah.
Okay, so that's an enormous amount actually of value, which is going
to be quite ironic given what the גמרא's Gemara's next thing the
גמרא's Gemara's going to say. אית לי גבך, Is li gabach, I
owe... you know, I have by you, meaning you owe to me.
I lent you once a... or I had you watch for me
this whatever קב kav is, I don't know five pounds of
saffron. יהביה לפלוני, Yahveih l'ploni, okay, and go ahead, that saffron that
you're holding onto for me, give it to this other guy, give
it to ראובן. Reuven. So it's like a מעמד שלשתן. ma'amad shloshtan.
You owe me this, it's my property in your possession, give it
to this third guy. באפי קאמינא לך Be'apei k'amina lach
and I'm telling you this in ראובן's Reuven's presence, I want you
to give it over to ראובן. Reuven. I'm telling you this in
ראובן's Reuven's presence, דלא הדרנא בי, delo hadarna bi, and that I
should not... and I'm not going to reverse myself. I'm telling you
in ראובן's Reuven's presence that I should not reverse myself. So the
גמרא Gemara says it sounds like he's only saying to do it
in the presence of the other guy as a way of getting
him to keep his word. So the גמרא Gemara says מכלל, micklal,
it sounds like from a legal perspective דאי בעי למהדר מצי הדר,
de'ee baei l'mehadr matzi hadar, that he can back out, that even
though he said give it to ראובן, Reuven, right, it sounds like
legally he would be able to back out, but he's just doing
and I'm saying this in front of ראובן Reuven to make sure
that I don't back out. So it sounds like as a matter
of law that he legally would be entitled to do such. Why
is that true? Why wouldn't it work because of מעמד שלשתן ma'amad
shloshtan and then he couldn't back out? So the גמרא Gemara says
הכי קאמר. hachi ka'amar. No, no, here's what it means. דברים הללו
לא ניתנו לחזרה. Devarim halalu lo nitnu lachazara. It means no, I'm
saying it in front of ראובן Reuven not to force me because
of embarrassment to not back out. I'm saying it in front of
ראובן Reuven so that it's legally binding and so there's not the
legal ability to back out. Okay, so basically saying I'm saying it
in front of ראובן Reuven so it's binding in principles of מעמד
שלשתן ma'amad shloshtan and now I won't be able to back
out. So the גמרא Gemara says הא אמר רב חדא זימנא. ha
amar Rav chada zimna.
Why does רב Rav have to say, why do we have to
teach this that he's, you know,
this idea of מעמד שלשתן, ma'amad shloshtan, didn't he already teach me
this הלכה? halacha? דאמר רב הונא אמר רב De'amar Rav Huna amar
Rav מנה לי בידך תנהו לפלוני במעמד שלשתן
קנה. maneh li b'yadcha tnahu l'ploni b'ma'amad shloshtan kana. And it works
and here he's talking about So why do you have to say
it? Now, of course, who says that he was saying it to
teach a halakhic principle? Maybe he was just actually employing this, you
know, it's an interesting story that he actually used it. But why
do you have to tell it to me? I already know that's
the הלכה. halakha. שכוייח, Shkoyach, he knows the הלכה. halakha. He wanted
to transfer his saffron. But okay, that's the גמרא's Gemara's question, why
is this being repeated in his name like it's telling me something
new? Didn't he already tell me this principle? So the גמרא Gemara
says, no, אי אשמעינן הוה אמינא הני מילי מתנה מרובה, ei ashmeinan
hava amina hani mili matana meruba, I might have thought when it's
a big gift, that's when you need all three people present, so
that then it's like a, it shows your seriousness to make it
work. But if it's a small gift, אבל מתנה מועטת לא ליבעי
בפניו, aval matana muetat lo libaye bifanav, I might have thought when
it's a big gift, that's when you need all three people present,
so that then it's like a, it shows your seriousness to make
it work. But if it's a small gift, maybe you could do
it even if all, if the all three parties weren't present, even
if the receiver was not present, קמשמע לן k'mashma lan even for
small gift. Now the small gift רש"י Rashi says is the saffron.
If you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says, I know, so
רש"י Rashi says, הני מילי, hani mili, but first of all, the
first רש"י Rashi says, הא אמר רב חדא זימנא ולמה ליה למימר
דלא מצינו הדרנא. ha-amar Rav chada zimna ve-lamah lei le-meimar de-lo matzina
hadarna. Now
why did he do the transfer with the saffron? Maybe just wanted
to do the transfer with the saffron. But why did he have
to make a point of turning that into a legal teaching? When
he said, I'm doing it with the saffron, he said: notice, I'm
not going to be able to be backing out, because this is
the principle of
מעמד שלשן, ma'amad shloshan, meaning שכוייח, shkoyach, you wanted to transfer the
saffron, but why did you make a point of emphasizing that this
was the principle and that you couldn't back out, you know? So
it seems like there's a חידוש chidush in that. We already know
that you've taught it before. Of course, you know, if it's a
big, you know, you might want to just use an opportunity to
re-teach it. But anyway, the גמרא's Gemara's answer is, הני מילי, hani
mili, I would have thought that that thing דבעינא בפניו de-ba-ina bifanav
that you need all three parties present, מתנה מרובה matana meruba when
it's a big one, כגון מנה, k'gon maneh, like a מנה maneh
which is like a hundred dollars. But here, you know, you might
have thought if it's a small little thing just transferring saffron, maybe
you don't need all people present, and רב Rav is emphasizing no,
you do. Of course the funny thing is, as Shaya pointed out,
that if it's saffron, it's a קב kav of saffron, it's probably
worth a lot more than a hundred dollars, so I don't know.
Yeah, yeah, there's no age as far as I know where saffron
was inexpensive in earlier times. Saffron was widely cultivated in Asia Minor
for use as a spice and the production of yellow dye. However,
the term מוריקא, amurika, saffron, is alternatively identified as safflower, false saffron,
sometimes used as a less costly substitute for saffron in the production
of dye.
Oh, that's interesting. Who says that?
It says תוספות Tosafot on 47a in גיטין. Gittin. Okay, whatever, fine.
All right, there you go. So maybe it wasn't saffron, it was
something else. All right, anyway, but that's the principle about מעמד שלשן
ma'amad shloshan and that's what was going on in the משנה Mishnah
according to some opinions. Okay, now we've taught this principle, now that
we've done with unpacking the משנה Mishnah and this principle that if
a guy says, you know, give this,
well, if it's a special thing of a מתנת שכיב מרע, matnas
shchiv mei-ra, it takes effect immediately, or מעמד שלשן ma'amad shloshan takes
effect immediately. Otherwise, it's a case like, you know, גט get or
a, or שטר שחרור shtar shichrur for a slave, it has to
reach the other party. Although a שטר שחרור shtar shichrur for a
slave, you know, if you actually handed it over, that's the debate
of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and the חכמים, Chachamim, maybe the other
side can, you know, maybe the שליח shaliach can just accept it
for, on behalf of the slave. So now we're going to deal
with other types of cases in which you're handing something over to
somebody to deliver and when will it take effect immediately and when
won't it? So let's take a look. Masat... oh, I'm sorry, we're
going to get to that in a minute. First we're going to
deal with another sort of מעמד שלשן ma'amad shloshan case. So first
another example of a מעמד שלשן ma'amad shloshan case. הנהו גינאי, Hanu
ginai, there were certain gardeners דעבדי חושבנא בהדי הדדי. d'avdi chushbana hadei
hadadi. They were doing their accounts, their books, you know, they had
lent money to each other during the growing season and they were,
you know, they were just like, you know, what do you call
it, balancing their books with one another, who owes who any money?
Okay, פש חמישה
אסתרי זוזי, pash chamisha istarei zuzei, so five
of these זוזי zuzei were left over, סלעים sla'im which were זוזי,
zuzei, which is basically like a, it's a certain coinage of a
cheaper coinage than the normal סלעים, sla'im, doesn't matter. You know, five
bucks was, was, you know, five bucks was left over, גבי חד
מינייהו gabei chad mineihu by one of them. One of them owed
five bucks to the rest. Okay, it's like you're, you know, when
you're like splitting the restaurant bill, right? So wait, this, that, whatever,
you had this, you had this, okay fine whatever fine I'll pay
twenty bucks everybody owes me three dollars. Okay fine, whatever it is.
So this guy owed five dollars to the rest of the gardeners.
Okay, גבי חד מינייהו. gabei chad mineihu.
אמרי ליה, Amri leh, they said to him, ויהבינן ניהליה למרי ארעא
באפי
מרי ארעא. v'yahvinun niyahlei l'marei ara b'apei marei ara. So they said,
you know what, the owner of the land is here, like we
all are sharecroppers on the land, you owe all of us five
bucks, let's just give it as a nice year-end bonus, it's funny,
they're giving it to
the, whatever, let's just give the five bucks to the guy who
owns the land. Okay. So okay, now they said this in the
presence of the owner of the land, so it's מעמד שלשן. ma'amad
shloshan. He owed the money to this group, this group basically transferred
the money that he owed them to the owner of the land,
and they said it in the presence of the owner of the
land.
and not only did he say yes fine but he even did
a קנין kinyan like you know like a handkerchief a קנין סודר
kinyan sudar to it to you know to underscore that he was
he was going to go through with it. You don't even need
it. The idea of מעמד שלשתן maamad sheloshtan it works without a
קנין kinyan just works verbally. But here he even did a קנין
kinyan to back it up. So now that five bucks has to
go to the owner of the land. Fine. Now ולסוף אזל עבד
חושבנא בין דיליה לנפשיה ulesof azal avad chushbena bein dilei lenafshei then
he went home and he reviewed the books and he realized wait
one minute we made a mistake I don't know anybody five dollars
okay. לא פש גביה
ולא מידי lo pash gabei velo midei he realized he didn't owe
anybody any money. All right now תוספות Tosafot says that they maybe
in the end they he showed them the books and they and
they admitted to it or it was just self-evident from the books
that they added wrong okay but something that's not debated you don't
need his נאמנות neemanut he showed them he came back and he
showed look guys we made a mistake I don't know anybody any
money. Okay so אתו לקמיה דרב נחמן ato lekamei deRav Nachman they
came to רב נחמן Rav Nachman said what should we do because
he already did a קנין kinyan that he'd pay five bucks to
the owner of the land but now it turns out that actually
we had done the math wrong. Okay so אמר להו amar lehu
he said מאי אעביד לכו mai aavid lacho רב נחמן Rav Nachman
says I'm sorry I can't help you you gotta give the five
bucks. Why? חדא דאמר רב הונא אמר רב chada deamar Rav Huna
amar Rav first of all רב הונא Rav Huna says in the
in the name of רב Rav that מעמד שלשתן maamad sheloshtan works
and you did a מעמד שלשתן. maamad sheloshtan. ועוד הא קנו מינך
veod ha kanu minach that you did a קנין kinyan so you
committed yourself to pay. Of course that seems a little bizarre because
he only committed himself to pay money he thought he owed which
he didn't owe so let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes with
it. אמר ליה רבא amar lei Rava so רבא Rava said to
him אטו האי מאי atu hai mai what's going on here? מי
קאמר לא יהבינא mi kaamar lo yahvina
he's not saying I refuse to give the money that I owe
then you could say you can't refuse מעמד שלשתן maamad sheloshtan you
did a קנין kinyan you can't back out. He's not saying I'm
backing out I'm refusing to pay. What he's saying is דליכא גבאי
קאמר delika gabai kaamar I don't have that money. I will agree
to pay all the money I owe to this guy. The problem
is the total amount that I owe is zero. Okay it's not
like I'm refusing to pay that money it's that I don't have
that money that money that you thought I had in my possession
that belonged to somebody else I don't have in my possession I
don't have anything that I owe to anybody else.
Okay so אמר ליה amar lei so רב נחמן Rav Nachman said
back to him oh okay אם כן קנין בטעות הוא im ken
kinyan betaut hu oh I didn't realize that. Meaning the way תוספות
Tosafot explains רב נחמן Rav Nachman misunderstood the case. רב נחמן Rav
Nachman thought right right תוספות Tosafot says רב נחמן Rav Nachman misunderstood
the specifics. רב נחמן Rav Nachman thought he was just refusing to
pay and he said oh I didn't realize that it wasn't he
wasn't that he was refusing he's that he was saying that he
didn't owe the money in the first place. So if that's the
case the whole thing was done בטעות betaut yes sure you did
a קנין סודר kinyan sudar but it was all based on a
mistake וכל קנין בטעות חוזר vechol kinyan betaut chozer and therefore it's
not binding. Fine so that was a case where מעמד שלשתן maamad
sheloshtan but it's not you know but it's only a מעמד שלשתן
maamad sheloshtan only works if it if it's building off of some
money that's owed to a certain party. When it turns out no
money was owed obviously nothing was binding.
The owner wasn't there.
He was there.
Oh he was there.
It says באפי מרי ארעא beapei marei ara in the presence of
the owner of the land. Okay. איתמר itmar now it was taught.
Now okay so that was the end of an example of מעמד
שלשתן. maamad sheloshtan. Now we're going to get back to cases that
are sort of discussing the case of the משנה Mishnah about giving
something to be delivered and what's the consequence when does it take
effect right away or otherwise. Okay so it was taught הולך מנה
לפלוני שאני חייב לו. holech maneh lePloni sheani chayav lo. I say
please deliver now okay now in the משנה Mishnah remember I say
תנו tenu okay give it to פלוני Ploni okay or so and
the גמרא Gemara before said תן כזכי. ten kezachi. If I say
give the גט get to my slave okay then give is translated
to mean you can take possession of it. So if you can
represent my slave's interest because זכין לאדם שלא בפניו zachin leadam shelo
befanyov you can take possession. That was the principle of תן כזכי.
ten kezachi. Here I'm not saying give I'm saying הולך holech okay
deliver. So let's take a look.
If you don't want him to have it why are you saying
הולך? holech?
You do want him to have it but you're not necessarily prepared
to give it to him right now. The חידוש chiddush of תן
כזכי ten kezachi is if you can represent my slave's interest I'm
prepared to have you take possession of it from right now.
If it gets lost along the way is it considered as if
it's in your pocket?
Well exactly let's take a look. So I say deliver a hundred
dollars to פלוני Ploni שאני חייב לו sheani chayav lo that I
owe him. Okay now you could say is this a case like
you can represent that guy's interest. I'm trying to pay off my
debt to this guy he did not appoint you a שליח shaliach
but maybe זכין לאדם שלא בפניו zachin leadam shelo befanyov like the
case of the עבד eved you can just automatically represent him and
take possession of it. So there's two questions. Number one is when
I say the word of הולך holech is that כזכי? kezachi? תן
ten we said is כזכי. kezachi. Is הולך כזכי? holech kizchi. When
I say הולך holech deliver maybe that means I want you clearly
just to be convey it to him. I do not want you
to take possession of it for him and I am not prepared
to have you take possession for him. So that's number one whether
my intent will allow you to do it. The other point is
maybe it's not in his interest for you to take possession of
that debt. You know why?
Exactly if you take
possession of that debt for him then I'm off the hook I'm
paid off and if that money gets lost along the way then
he doesn't get his hundred dollars. So he doesn't want you... Exactly.
If you take possession of that debt for him then I'm off
the hook, I'm paid up. And if that money gets lost along
the way then he doesn't get his hundred dollars. So he doesn't
want you to take possession of it for him. Okay, so there's
two good reasons why we should say that I am not off
the hook when I give you that money. So let's take a
look. הוליך מנה לפלוני שאני חייב לו Holich maneh l'ploni she'ani chayav
lo אמר רב Amar Rav חייב באחריותו chayav b'achrayuso
so I am still responsible for it's, you know, for it's anything
that happens to it. Meaning I have not yet paid up my
debt yet. If the money gets lost I still have to I
owe the guy the money. Okay, cause he doesn't want you to
the debt to be paid up yet. One minute. Okay, so that
might be, let's keep on reading. חייב באחריותו chayav b'achrayuso ואם בא
לחזור אינו חוזר v'im ba lachzor eino chozer but
it's a middle position. I cannot say to the שליח shaliach wait,
wait, wait, wait, wait, bring the money back, I'll pay him later,
I'll pay him when I see him. Okay, so it's a very
bizarre position. Basically the idea is is that it's totally done in
the interests of the person, of the creditor. And what we say
is, so I give this to חנן Chanan here and I say
חנן Chanan go bring this to Charlie I owe him the hundred
dollars. So it's not in Charlie's interest חנן Chanan for you to
represent Charlie to take full possession of the money, to have the
debt paid off because then because he doesn't want for then, you
know, if the money got lost he'd be out it. So you
do not represent him to have the debt paid off. But you
do represent him enough that you take it's a very interesting position
that you take possession of it to prevent me from telling you
to bring the money give the money back. So there's a very
interesting sort of middle position. You take possession of it for on
Charlie's behalf that I can't back out, but not so much that
it would actually that Charlie would lose anything in the transaction. So
you therefore the debt is not yet paid off. So somehow you
can hold it on behalf of Charlie in a way that I
can't demand it back, but not in a way that the debt
is yet paid off.
So he still owes him the hundred bucks he still has to
pay you back then, right?
Yeah, it's not his money, right?
No, he's supposed to pay him back the other guy.
Yeah, right. I mean, it's not yet the other guy's money, it's
still my money.
I'm supposed to be able to retract. What? Why shouldn't he be?
Well, that's going to be what the next line is going to
be. So let's take a look. But his point is is it
possible to be a middle position? That you can say no, I'm
holding it on be on behalf of someone, right? And I'm not
going to give it back to you because Charlie wants his money
back and I'm holding onto it for his sake. He doesn't own
it yet, but it's being held for his sake and I'm right,
and I'm representing now now the question is why am I okay
with that? Maybe you know so so let's take a look, okay?
So he says like this. ואם בא לחזור אינו חוזר v'im ba
lachzor eino chozer ושמואל אמר u'Shmuel amar מתוך שחייב באחריותו mitoch she'chayav
b'achrayuso no, no, no,
you can't have it both ways. If Charlie does not if I'm
still obligated for the what happens to that money, so the debt
is not yet paid off. If the debt is not yet paid
off, so it's still my money. אי בא לחזור חוזר iy ba
lachzor chozer I can get I can have say give it back.
There's no middle position. Either the debt is paid off and then
I'm off the hook, or it's not paid off and I can
retract. There's no middle position. So the גמרא Gemara let's see how
the גמרא Gemara analyzes this. גמרא Gemara says לימא בהא קמיפלגי leima
b'ha kamifligi let's say this is the debate. מר סבר הוליך כזכי
דמי mar savar holich k'zachi damei
one says when I say go pay, you know, go bring this
to Charlie, הוליך holich is like זכי. zachi. It's like I'm saying
take possession of it for Charlie, right? Because that's the question also,
A: can he represent Charlie's interest, B: am I okay with what's
about to transpire if she wants to seize it for Charlie. So
one position is הוליך כזכי. holich k'zachi. I do say I'm okay
with him seizing it for Charlie. And therefore it's not in Charlie's
interest for him to seize it completely, as we've said, but it
is in Charlie's interest for him to seize it enough that I
cannot demand it back. But I have to be okay with that,
right? Because if I basically don't want Charlie to have any rights
to it till the debt's paid off, what entitles him to restrict
me that way? Okay, so I have to be basically totally okay
with him taking control of it for Charlie and then Charlie's in
the best position because חנן Chanan has taken control of it enough
to prevent me from doing retracting, but not enough that Charlie the
debt is actually paid off yet. But it but it starts with
not only that it's in Charlie's interest, but that I'm okay with
that הוליך כזכי, holich k'zachi, I'm okay with him taking possession of
it. Okay? ומר סבר u'mar savar and the other one says שמואל
Shmuel that says
no, it's all or nothing, הוליך לאו כזכי דמי holich lav k'zachi
damei no I'm not okay with him taking any possession of it
at all. So it's totally in my possession and therefore I can
retract myself. So the גמרא Gemara says no, that would seem a
debate, but the גמרא Gemara says no, שמואל Shmuel is going further
than that. לא דכולי עלמא הוליך כזכי דמי lo d'chulei alma holich
k'zachi damei שמואל Shmuel in principle could agree הוליך כזכי. holich k'zachi.
I would be okay with him taking possession of it for Charlie
if he would take full possession, if I'd be off the hook.
Okay, שמואל Shmuel does not have a problem with that I'm prepared
for Charlie to take possession of it. The problem is you can't
have a middle position. You can't take partial possession. Okay, so והכא
בהא קמיפלגי v'hacha b'ha kamifligi this is the debate. מר סבר לא
אמרינן מיגו mar savar lo amrinan migu we don't say since you
are, you know, since I'm still responsible I can retract. No, we're
allowed for a middle position. possession where he's taken partial possession of
it. ומר U'mar and שמואל's Shmuel of the opinion אמרינן מיגו amrinan
migo that we say since. No, since you're still responsible if they
get lost, then the other guy doesn't own the money yet, and
if he doesn't own the money yet, I'm entitled to retract. Okay,
so everybody agrees that חנן's Chanan going to act in Charlie's best
interest. Everybody agrees that I am prepared for the debt to be
fully paid off as of this minute. Okay, and I'm entitling חנן,
Chanan, I'm empowering חנן Chanan to take possession of it for Charlie.
The question is can you have a middle state where the other
side controls it enough that I can't back off but at the
same time he can say I haven't had I'm not considering the
debt paid yet? Okay, and רב Rav, says yes, you can hold
it for somebody with preventing me from getting the money back with
the debt still not being paid. And שמואל Shmuel says no, I'm
sorry. If you haven't paid the debt yet, then it's all your
money and you can ask it back.
Specifically הולך holech as opposed to תן. ten.
No,
תן ten would even more be כזכי. kezachi? We've already established that
תן ten is כזכי. kizchi. Here it's even הולך כזכי. holech kizchi
That's
going to be the ongoing question for today whether הולך כזכי holech
kezachi? or not.
Yeah, let's look at it the other way around. Let's say Charlie
then sends חנן Chanan over to you to you know for the
debt to come or wherever it is and he says I want
it to be some sort of middle position where you know...
Well, according to רב, Rav if a middle position is possible and
I'm okay with it, then why not? רב Rav allows for it.
Yeah, what would he have to but what would he say?
I'm חנן, Chanan, I'm sending you. We're actually going to see a
case like that. I am sending you to collect my debt but
I'm not telling but I'm telling you that I will not consider
it paid until I get the money in my pocket. If I'm
stupid enough to give חנן Chanan the money and go along with
that, then according to רב Rav that such a phenomenon can exist.
But he'd have to be informed. Meaning חנן Chanan would have to
tell you that. Yeah, in other words if he just סתם stam
comes to you from Charlie and you're willing to give it to
him, then then you're already off the hook, right?
Right, presumably if he's a שליח shaliach and I don't know otherwise
or whatever, then that means that he's empowered him that he's fully
acquired it and taken possession. But yeah, but רב Rav. allows for
such a strange middle position.
Yeah, and what about מיגו? migo? Is the מיגו migo is it
since he could have said תן ten but said הולך holech or
is it since he's responsible?
No, the second. And it's not מיגו migo like we use other
times. Other times we use מיגו, migo, it's a very technical term
that means like I'm believed about A because I could have claimed
B. Here it just means here it doesn't have the technical meaning.
Here it only means like that you know שמואל's Shmuel argument is
that you can't have it halfway. Okay? So all מיגו migo here
means is that שמואל's Shmuel point that you don't have such a
middle position that if you're going to be able if the debt
isn't paid, then the other side does not have cannot take partial
possession of it. Okay? That's all it means. It's not a generic
it's not the general sort of technical idea of מיגו. migo. No,
no. It's just תוספות's Tosafot שמואל's Shmuel sort of logical position that
you can't have it halfway. Okay? Or you can't have it both
ways depending on how you want to look at it. Okay, anyway.
All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Exactly. Well,
that's exactly it. Okay, the גמרא Gemara says, okay, תניא כוותיה
דרב. tanya k'vasay d'Rav. Now we learned like רב. Rav הולך מנה
לפלוני, holech maneh l'ploni, deliver this מנה maneh to this so-and-so שאני
חייב לו sh'ani chayav lo that I owe him. תן מנה לפלוני
שאני חייב לו ten maneh l'ploni sh'ani chayav lo or give it
to him. הולך מנה לפלוני פיקדון שיש לו בידי holech maneh l'ploni
pikadon she-yesh lo b'yadi or go ahead and bring him this פיקדון
pikadon that I owe him. תן מנה לפלוני פיקדון שיש לו בידי
ten maneh l'ploni pikadon she-yesh lo b'yadi or give. So whether you
say הולך holech or whether you say תן, ten, whether it's money
that's owed or a פיקדון pikadon that's owed, okay, so in all
those cases חייב
באחריות chayav b'achrayut you're still responsible if anything gets lost ואם בא
לחזור אינו חוזר v'im ba lachazor eino chozer but you cannot retract.
Once you've given it over to this other guy, this guy now
can take possession of it enough to prevent to to say I
refuse to give it back to you, I'm holding onto it for
for Charlie.
Okay, so there is
no difference between תן ten and הולך holech then? There is no
difference. That's the point of this ברייתא braita to say whether you
said תן, ten, whether you said הולך, holech whether it's a מנה,
maneh, whether it's a פיקדון, pikadon, in no matter what in all
those cases you can't retract and but you're still responsible. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this, לימא leima
okay, so the גמרא Gemara says פיקדון. pikadon. Wait a minute. By
a פיקדון, pikadon, why can't
why why can חנן Chanan if I'm giving back Charlie's nice gold
watch to חנן Chanan to deliver not a hundred dollars, then why
do we assume that חנן Chanan is זוכה? zocheh? Until now he's
been great. He's he's totally served this other side's interest. He prevented
me from coming back and he you know it's not yet paid
up which is perfect. Like the other guy is in the is
golden, is exactly in the best position. But the ברייתא braita says
wait a minute, if it's a פיקדון pikadon the other side isn't
golden because if I'm giving him my golden watch, okay, Charlie's gold
watch, okay, you know very expensive watch, the other side says it's
all very nice that Rabbi Linsten here is still חייב באחריות chayav
b'achrayut until I get the thing or whatever, but you know that's
a really expensive watch, that has a lot of sentimental value like
I don't care about the money, I don't want anybody handling it,
I only trust Rabbi Linsten to handle it. So I'm not okay
with חנן Chanan just self-representing himself. you know, you know, just I
didn't appoint חנן *Chanan* a שליח shliach. *shaliach*, you know, so why,
why can he, why is he seen as my representative to take
possession of that for me? It's not in my interest for anybody
other than Rabbi Linzer to be handling that watch, okay? So by
פיקדון *pikadon*, why doesn't he say לימא ליה *leima leh*, why doesn't
why don't me who gave it, now of course I was the
one who gave it to חנן *Chanan*, but nevertheless, I can say
to חנן *Chanan*, חנן *Chanan*, you can't take possession of that for
Charlie. Charlie maybe doesn't want you handling it altogether. Of course I
was the one who gave it to חנן *Chanan* to give to
Charlie, but nevertheless we can't assume that Charlie is representing חנן *Chanan*'s
interest, חנן *Chanan* is representing Charlie's interest by holding onto that. לימא
ליה *leima leh*, let me say to him, where were we? אין
רצונו שיהא פקדונן בידך *ein retzono sheyehei pikdono beyadecha*.
You know what? Charlie doesn't want anybody else handling this watch, okay?
So give it back to me. I was wrong to have given
it to you. Give it back to me, I'll give it to
Charlie. Oh no, I'm holding onto it. Oh, you can't say you're
representing his interests. He doesn't want anybody else handling holding onto it.
Give it back to me, I'll give it to Charlie. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, אמר רב זירא כשהוחזק כפרן *amar Rav Zeira
keshehuchzak kafran*. No, no, no. You're right, in a normal case you
could say that, and you could demand the פיקדון *pikadon* back. But
here the case was, was that I've been denying for the last
two years since I really had my eye on that watch. So
anytime Charlie asked for it, I denied that I had it. What
are you talking about? Watch? Who knows? What watch? What are you
talking about? So finally my conscience got the better of me. It's
ערב ראש השנה *erev Rosh Hashanah*, okay, I'm doing some תשובה *teshuva*,
my conscience got the better of me, in that case, you know
what? It isn't in Charlie's interest that somebody else hold onto that
watch other than me, okay? Because I might my יצר הרע *yetzer
hara* might kick in again, okay? So that's why. So basically what
we've said is, we allow for a middle position that once that
I've given it over, so I'm okay with the other side taking
possession. This שליח shliach *shaliach* is seen as automatically representing the interests
of the other side. And it's the possible middle position where the
other's the debt is not yet paid, the פיקדון *pikadon*'s not yet
returned, but I can't retract. And even in a case of פיקדון
*pikadon* where we could say I should be able to retract because
I could claim it's not in the other side's interest for somebody
else to be holding onto it, no, there are cases when it
is in the clearly that's better for the other side, and when
it clearly is better for the other side, it's the same idea
that I'm still responsible and I can't retract.
Yeah. Go back to a בר יוסף Yosef *Bar Yosef* situation, שעתא
דאורחיה לשיורי *shata de'orchei
leshiyurei*.
It's a good point, you know, why the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* isn't
concerned about that. I guess the difference is that before we were
dealing with something that was like a קניין *kinyan*, like you know,
a mechanism for transferring, you know, ownership, and there you're not going
to say, well, for you הגבהה *hagbah* works and for somebody else
it doesn't, for you משיכה *meshichah* works. It's like a mechanism for
transferring property. Whereas here we're talking about whether somebody becomes another person's
representative. So it's not the question isn't like the mechanism, it's like
on the evaluation of the protagonists.
But yes, but it is true, it is case by case. I
mean, that is true, it's sort of like the difference between the
גט *get* and שטר שחרור *shtar shichrur*, like can we say, you
know, when do we say you represent the other side might be
somewhat case by case, you know, dependent. Now of course you are
right, because really like what would the חכמים *chachamim* say in a
case where clearly this שליח shliach, *shaliach* or this slave was like,
I mean in Rome they used to have it, like that slaves
could own slaves and they could be very wealthy or whatever. You
know, what would they do if in a particular case it actually
was clear that it was in the slave's interest to remain a
slave? Right? Would the חכמים *chachamim* say okay, well in that case
it doesn't work? Or would they sort of say, no, no, no,
like we have to be categorical about it? So you're right, like
even in some of these questions about, you know, when are you
seen as representing the other side, you know, but the sense one
gets is, putting the חכמים *chachamim*'s זכין *zachin* by slaves aside, that
that issue do we say זכין לאדם שלא בפניו *zachin leadam shelo
befanav*, we do evaluate case by case. One minute, do we say
זכין *zachin* here? Is it in the person's interest or not in
the person's interest? You know, and that does seem from the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* that that is a case by case assessment. Yeah.
But יצחק *Yitzchak* would presumably agree though הולך holech, כתן *holech keten*.
Is כזכי kizchi. *kezaki* middle ground?
But if
I said זכי
*zachi* then that's total.
No, no. No, no, no. That's what I'm saying. הולך holech כתן
*holech keten*, 100 percent כזכי kezachi *kezaki*. I would be happy for
Charlie to own it 100 percent. From my side I want him
to take full possession of it. Charlie is not prepared to have
חנן *Chanan* take full possession of it. In Charlie's interest is for
חנן *Chanan* to only take partial possession of it. So I'm prepared
for it to be fully taken over, the other side's in their
interest only half taken. And that's why it's in this middle position.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this.
No circumstance unless you know Charlie for sure would be okay if
from the very beginning or
Charlie made him a שליח shliach *shaliach*, yeah.
Unless you're a scoundrel, in which case he wants it out of
your hand and into the other.
Ah, yes, but he wants it out of my hands, but he
doesn't want it paid back yet. He wants, it's always in his
interest to have a middle position that I can't retract, but it
hasn't yet been paid back until he receives it. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. רב ששת Rav Sheshet, *Rav
Sheshet*, now we're going to have some cases. רב ששת Rav Sheshet
*Rav Sheshet*, now we're going to have some cases. He had sold
some סרבלאי, some coats, if you look at רש״י, Rashi, coats בלעז.
balaz. See that רש״י, Rashi, eight lines from the bottom, coats בלעז.
balaz. Anyway, he had sold some coats in מחוזא Machuza and people
owed him money and he was trying to collect from his debtors,
from the people who he had given credit. Okay, so אמר ליה
amar lei רב יוסף בר חמא. Rav Yosef bar Chama. So he
said רב יוסף בר חמא Rav Yosef bar Chama who was on
his way to מחוזא. Machuza. He said to him, you know what?
בהדי דאתית behadei de-asit on your way back, אייתינהו ניהלי, aitinu nihali,
bring it to me. If you wouldn't mind stopping by, maybe he
was like, you know, a collector, big guy, big muscles or whatever.
Anyway, if you wouldn't mind stopping by to the people that owe
me the money and bring it back to me next time you
visit מחוזא. Machuza. Okay, so he is going. Now here I am
appointing him a שליח. shliach Okay, it's very clear, you don't even
need any זך zach in principle. I explicitly appointed him a שליח
shaliach, and I'm asking him to collect the debt from these people.
Okay, so אזל azal he went, יהבו ניהליה. yehavu nihaleh. They gave
him the money they owed him. אמרו ליה amru leh they said
to him, נקני מינך. nikni minach. So you know, let's do a
קנין kinyan from you, a קנין סודר, kinyan sudar, that you basically
will agree that if anything goes wrong and the money gets lost
or whatever, that we're fully paid up, that our debt is paid
back, we're done. אמר להו אין. amar lehu in. He said fine.
לסוף אישתמיט להו. lesof ishtamit lehu. So
in the end though, he avoided them. He never actually did the
קנין kinyan to agree that the debt would be considered fully paid
up. Okay, so basically he was in the position that was the
best to represent this other side's interest. He had possession of the
money, but the debt was not paid up until the money was
actually delivered, okay, which is perfect for this other side. Okay, כי
אתא לקמיה דרב ששת, ki ata lekamei de-Rav Sheshet, when he came
to רב ששת, אמר ליה amar leh so רב ששת said to
him, שפיר עבדת דלא, shappir abadt de-la,
you did good that you did
not obligate yourself to be responsible if something went wrong. דלא שוית
נפשך עבד לוה לאיש מלוה, delo shaveit nafshech eved loveh le-ish malveh,
you should not make yourself to fulfill this פסוק pasuk that said
that the debtor is a slave to the creditor. So don't put
yourself in their debt, don't agree to be responsible if something goes
wrong, okay? It's like the opposite for, like, declining the insurance. Here
you decline being liable. Okay, so anyway, don't be liable for it.
I don't want the debt to be paid until I get the
money and you should not have agreed to be liable if something
went wrong. Okay, לשנא אחרינא, lishna achrina, another version is he said,
שפיר עבדת, shappir abadt, you did good not to agree to be
liable to them if something went wrong. Why? Why did you do
good? עבד לוה לאיש מלוה. eved loveh le-ish malveh. They're my debtors,
they're my servants, meaning
they're responsible, they're fully responsible until the debt is paid off. Why
should you agree to assume some of that responsibility? I sent you
to bring the money to me, but they should not be off
the hook until I get the money and you did good to
refuse to agree to get them off the hook. So here we
see that even if the creditor makes the guy a שליח, shaliach
he could make him a שליח only to limit it to his
best interest. I want you to be a שליח to receive the
money but not to consider the debt paid off now. On my
side though, if the guy comes and says, ראובן Reuven wants his
money, give me the money, I'll bring it to him, and I'll
say, if I'm not considered to have paid off the debt by
giving it to you, I'm not giving it to you. I'm only
waiting to give it to him. I'm entitled to do that, okay?
Every side should serve to defend their own best interest,
you know, meaning you should, don't you have the right to assume
that if he's sending the guy?
Apparently not. Apparently not. Why? We should assume that everybody's acting in
their own best interest. Okay, so now, of course if I say,
go tell him that I won't give you the money until he
agrees that I'm
paid off once I've given it to you, okay, then we'll get
him to agree to that. Okay, you know, life isn't what you
deserve, it's what you negotiate. So the גמרא Gemara says like this:
רב אחא ברבי יאשיה, Rav Achai berabi Yoshiya, no I did not
make that one up. רב אחא, Rav Achai, they tell that one
in these books that talk about how to negotiate for your salary
or something, right? You don't get what you deserve in life, you
get what you negotiate. Okay, רב אחא ברבי יאשיה הוה ליה איספקא
דכספא בנהרדעא. Rav Achai berabi Yoshiya hava lei ishpaka de-chaspa be-Nahardea. Now
he, someone in נהרדעא Nahardea was holding onto a goblet of silver
of his. I think that's what an איספקא ishpaka is, a goblet
of silver. Is that what the English says? A goblet or something?
It's like the יוסף story.
Right, exactly. A goblet of silver of his in נהרדעא. Nahardea. Okay,
he wanted to retrieve it. אמר להו לרב דוסתאי amar lehu le-Rav
Dostai ברבי ינאי berabi Yannai ולרב יוסף ברבי קיפר, u-le-Rav Yosef berabi
Keifar, so he said to these two rabbis,
בהדי דאתיתו be-hadei de-atitu on your way back from that place, where
was it? In נהרדעא, Nahardea, bring it to me. So I'm trying
to get my goblet back, all right. אזלו azalu so they went,
יהבו ניהליהו, yehavu nihalehu, they gave these rabbis the goblet to bring
back. אמרו להו amru lehu they said to him,
נקני מינייכו. nikni minaychu. Well, wait, wait, wait. We're going to do,
after they gave the goblet, they realized they were a little too
quick to give them the goblet and they were... We want you
to do a קנין Kinyan to agree that now we're done, that
you're, if anything goes wrong it's your
responsibility, we're done, we've paid back, given back the goblet. So אמרי
להו, Amri lehu, לא! Lo! No! Sorry! No!
So אמרי להו, Amri lehu, so, so אמרי להו, Amri lehu, they
said back, אחזי לן, Ahizei lan, fine, give us the goblet back.
So, which they don't have to do, as we've been learning, they
can hold on to the goblet,
right, until you know they have the best of both worlds here.
רב דוסתאי ברבי ינאי Rav Dustai b'Rebbi Yannai אמר להו, Amar lehu,
איטין, Itin, fine, you want the goblet back? Yes, okay. רבי יוסי
בר קיפר Rebbi Yosef bar Kifar אמר להו Amar lehu לא, Lo,
no, I'm not giving you the goblet back, we're holding on to
it, and you're, you're still not off the hook. הוו קא מצערו
ליה, Havu ka mtzaru lei, so they were giving this רבי יוסי
בר קיפר Rebbi Yosef bar Kifar a hard time, they were maybe
beating him up and saying, give us back the goblet, we're not
agreeing to this. So, אמר ליה חזי מר היכי עביד, Amar lei
chazi mar heichei avid, so, so then he, רבי יוסי בר קיפר,
Rebbi Yosef bar Kifar, that was being beaten up because
remember רב דוסתאי Rav Dustai was prepared to give it back, so
he said to רב דוסתאי, Rav Dustai, look what they're doing to
me, they're beating me up,
so חזי מר היכי עביד, chazi mar heichei avid, what they're doing.
אמר להו טב, Amar lehu tov, good! רמו ליה, Ramu lei, beat
him up! So go like, he was not helping out, he said
you know they should be good, it's good that they're beating you
up, give them the goblet back, okay? So which is a little
interesting, I mean he's not representing the side of the person he
was sent for. So כי אתו לגבי, Ki atu legabei, when they
finally came back to, who was it? רבי אושעיא. Rebbi Oshaya. אמר
ליה, Amar lei, רבי אושעיא Rebbi Oshaya said,
I'm sorry, what's his name said, the one who's being beaten up,
רבי
יוסי בר קיפר, Rebbi Yosef bar Kifar, חזי מר, chazi mar, did
you see? לא מיסתייא דלא סייען אלא אמר להו נמי טב רמו
ליה. Lo mistiya d'lo siyan ela amar lehu nami tov ramu lei.
Look! So he said, did you see what this, you know, what
רב דוסתאי Rav Dustai did? Not only did he not help me
out when I was being beaten up and represent your interests, he
said to these guys, it's good that you're beating him up. So
what, what was this? So אמר ליה אמאי תעביד הכי, Amar lei
amai tavit hachi, why'd you do that? Why'd you not defend, you
know, my interests, why'd you say beat him up, you know, what's
going on here? אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said to him, look,
you don't understand the people we were dealing with. אותם בני אדם,
Otam bnei adam, those people, הן אמה, Hen ama, they are like
an אמה, Ama, now it, it must be, I don't know what
that means, an אמה's Ama only a cubit, but whatever, who knows,
whatever, you know, they're, I don't know, they're, just something is, they're
like meaning, meaning the people of great stature, they're huge,
okay? הן אמה וכובען אמה, Hen ama v'kovam ama, their helmets are
an אמה, Ama, ומדברין מחציהן, u'medabrin me'chatzehen, they talk from their like
diaphragm, from their centers, they, they have thundering voices, okay? These are
like big important חשובי chashuvei people who can beat us up. ושמותיהם
מבוהלים, U'shmoteihem mevuvalin, their very names instill terror in people. What are
their names? ארדא וארתא ופילי בריש. Arda v'Arta u'Pili Barish. So, and
whatever, so anyway,
what?
Very frightening names. אומרין כפתו, Omrin kfotu, if they say, you know,
put somebody in, in, you know, in chains, כפתין, koftin, then they'll
be bound up. אומרין הרוגו, Omrin harogu, if they say execute somebody,
הרגין, hargin, then that person gets executed. So, you know what,
it wasn't my own selfish, like just self-preservation here that I agreed
to give them the goblet back. What was I going to say?
אי הרגוהו לדוסטאי, Iy harguvei l'Dustai, if they had killed דוסתאי, Dustai,
מי נתן לינאי אבא בר כמותי, mi nasan l'Yannai abba bar kamosi,
who would have given ינאי Yannai my father a son in my
exchange instead of me? Right, this is רב דוסתאי ברבי ינאי, Rav
Dustai b'Rebbi Yannai, you know what? I was like a little just
preserving my life there, okay? So that's why I agreed to give
the cup back. That's why when this you was saying, oh, look
what they're beating me up, I had to side with them, okay?
So and they agreed, so they really,
yeah, of course, obviously it was not, you know, legally I should
have refused to give it, but I was a little bit just
saving myself there, okay. אמר ליה בני אדם הללו, Amar lei bnei
adam elu, those, so he said, these people, קרובים למלכות הן, krovim
l'malchusa hein, do they have connections with the government? אמר ליה הן,
Amar lei hein, so he said הן, hein, yes. Meaning, and they
can get away with what they want with whatever they would do.
יש להם סוסים ופרדים שרצים אחריהם, Yesh lahem susim u'predim she'ratzim achareihem,
do they have horses and mules that run after them? אמר ליה
הן, Amar lei hein, yes. אמר ליה, Amar lei, oh, okay, אי
הכי שפיר עבדת, iy hachi shappir avadt, then that was good, that
was smart, you should have just given them the cup back. All
right, anyway, a nice little humorous
break.
Roman Empire was like a fascist dictatorship, I guess. Anyway, the principle
being, it's all very nice about what you're legally entitled to, but
you know you need to assess the situation.
All right, and now we just understanding, so the guys, you know,
there's two, you and Charlie case, and then you send me, right?
So you obviously want Charlie to be, you know, I want the
other to always be obligated, I want to be completely, you know,
off the hook, right? So me as a שליח, right? So I
can't say yes to anything, right? Because in other words I'm not
allowed
to.
Oh, that's an interesting question. If you were to do a קנין
kinyan that said that Charlie was off the hook,
are you doing like who, since when did I empower you that
way, right? Maybe you're accepting responsibility to me if something goes wrong.
It's a very good point. Like in all these discussions it sounds
like if they had done a קנין kinyan Charlie would be off
the hook, right? Why is that? Like am I implicitly when I
make you a שליח saying that if you
get the best deal that you can and if you do a
קנין kinyan then ostensibly you're acting on my representing my interests or
are you just obligating yourself with that קנין? kinyan? That's a very
good question. I have to check into that. Yeah, that's a good
point. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. That was a whole interesting thing about a middle status where
we sort of established that הולך holech was כזכי kezachi but that
the other side only wants to take partial possession and according to
רב they're able to. Now we're going to continue with this. הולך
מנה לפלוני. holech maneh leploni. I go say to Michael here, Michael
go ahead bring this hundred dollars to Jonathan there and maybe it's
not even paying off a debt, I'm just giving him a gift,
okay? So it's a gift and הולך holech is כזכי kezachi then
as soon as I say go ahead and deliver it to him,
then you should take possession of it for him,
right? והולך וביקשו veholech uviksho not Jonathan, somebody else, go for ראובן.
Reuven. והולך וביקשו ולא מצאו. veholech uviksho velo matzao. And then you
went to look find him and you couldn't find him, okay? Because
the reason you couldn't find him is he had died, okay? So
in that
case תני חדא tani chada one ברייתא braita teaches יחזרו למשלח yachzeru
lameshaleach bring it back to me. ותני אידך vetani idach the other
ברייתא braita teaches ליורשי מי שנשתלח לו leyorshei mi shenishtalach lo
to ראובן's Reuven children. Okay so basically it's the question with as
soon as I say go ahead and bring this hundred dollars to
ראובן, Reuven, did ראובן Reuven take possession at that moment? If the
answer is yes, then even if ראובן Reuven is dead then ראובן's
Reuven kids get it. If ראובן Reuven didn't take possession and ראובן
Reuven is dead then you bring it back to me. So that
seems to be a debate of whether הולך holech is כזכי kezachi.
until now we've been assuming הולך holech is כזכי. kezachi Okay. So
לימא בהא קמיפלגי leima beha kamiflegi let's say this is the debate.
מר סבר הולך כזכי ומר סבר הולך לאו כזכי mar savar holech
kezachi umar savar holech lav kezachi whether as soon as I say
bring this hundred dollars to ראובן Reuven whether it means ביזכי bizchei
in it for ראובן Reuven and whether ראובן Reuven owns it immediately.
Okay. So אמר אבא בר
ממל Amar Abba bar Memel ובכולי עלמא הולך לאו כזכי uvechuli alma
holech lav kezachi everybody would say הולך holech is not כזכי kezachi
which is quite fascinating because until this moment we were assuming that
everybody said הולך holech is כזכי kezachi. and we had a ברייתא
braita that said it explicitly. Okay but now we're going to say
it's not כזכי. kezachi If it's not כזכי kezachi why would it
go to ראובן's Reuven heirs? Okay. So ובכולי עלמא הולך לאו כזכי
uvechuli alma holech lav kezachi ולא קשיא הא בברי הא בשכיב מרע.
velo kashya ha bebari ha beshchiv mera. The case where you deliver
it to ראובן's Reuven heirs is when the person saying bring this
hundred dollars to ראובן Reuven is on his deathbed. So the reason
you give it to the heirs of ראובן Reuven is ראובן Reuven
doesn't own the money. The only yes it is true in this
case ראובן Reuven when the guy's on his deathbed ראובן Reuven owns
the money as soon as the money is given. Not because הולך
holech is כזכי kezachi but because it's a deathbed bequest and a
deathbed bequest takes effect right away. Okay so in general הולך holech
is not כזכי kezachi and ראובן Reuven doesn't get the money till
it arrives to him and if he's dead it goes back, but
in a deathbed bequest it does work,
okay? ורב זביד אמר הא והא בשכיב מרע veRav Zevid amar ha
veha beshchiv mera they're both deathbed bequests. Again
once again saying הולך holech is not כזכי kezachi. against what we
said
earlier. So of a case of ברי bari ראובן Reuven does not
own the
money. The only way ראובן Reuven can own the money is because
it was a deathbed bequest. If it's a deathbed bequest what's the
issue? Then of course it should go to
ראובן's Reuven heirs. הדא דאיתא למקבל בשעת מתנתו והא דליתא למקבל בשעת
מתנתו. hada de'isa lemakabel besha'as matnaso veha delaisa lemakabel besha'as matnaso. Now
the question is when did ראובן Reuven die? Okay? So if the
guy in his deathbed bequest said give a hundred dollars to ראובן
Reuven if ראובן Reuven was already dead at that time it didn't
take effect. If ראובן Reuven was alive then it took effect and
then ראובן Reuven died and then it goes to ראובן's Reuven heirs,
okay? So different ways of explaining the debate but quite interesting that
the גמרא Gemara is trying to argue against what we said before
that הולך holech is not כזכי. kezachi And the reason it would
work would be because of some way in which it was a
deathbed bequest,
okay? הדא דאיתא בשעת מתנה. hada de'isa besha'as matana. רב פפא אמר
הא והא בברי Rav Pappa amar ha veha bebari okay the guy
is healthy. So then why is it going to work? Is it
going to be because הולך כזכי? Holeich kizachi, No, there's going to
be a different reason it's going to work. What's the issue? הא
דמית מקבל בחיי נותן והא דמית נותן בחיי מקבל. ha demis mekabel
bechayei nosen veha demis nosen bechayei mekabel. What happened was the guy
who sent a hundred dollars he said הולך holech this money to
ראובן. Reuven. He's healthy. Okay ראובן's Reuven healthy, the guy's healthy, whatever,
okay? So why will ראובן Reuven own the money own the money
not because הולך holech is כזכי kezachi but because the משלח meshaleach
then dies. משלח meshaleach dies so what? הולך Holeich. isn't כזכי kizachi,
but there's another principle: somebody said something and then he died even
though he was healthy, מצוה לקיים דברי המת. mitzvah lekayem divrei hamess.
So we deliver it to
ראובן. Reuven. order to fulfill the wishes that the person expressed before
he died, which is not a deathbed bequest. Deathbed bequest automatically takes
effect. מצוה לקיים דברי המת Mitzvah lekayeim divrei hameis means the heirs
have a responsibility to fulfill the wishes of the guy. Okay, so
when it says you deliver it to ראובן's Reuven heirs, it was
basically that first the guy died, the משלח Meshaleach died, that created
a responsibility on the משלח's Meshaleach heirs to satisfy his wishes, then
ראובן Reuven died, fine, so you can give it to ראובן, Reuven,
you give it to ראובן's Reuven heirs because it was possible to
give it to ראובן Reuven after the משלח Meshaleach died. But if
first ראובן Reuven died and then the משלח Meshaleach died, so when
the משלח Meshaleach died and it became דברי המת, divrei hameis, ראובן
Reuven was already dead and the wishes couldn't be fulfilled at that
moment, then there's no מצוה לקיים דברי המת. Mitzvah lekayeim divrei hameis.
Wait, can I argue otherwise? I can say like listen, you know,
I'm the son of whoever it is that sends it. Like, the
son can say, listen, you know, these two guys had a really
good relationship, he had no kids.
Right, it could be. I understand. The idea you are correct. The
idea that you would say מצוה לקיים דברי המת Mitzvah lekayeim divrei
hameis since it's not an automatic transfer of the property, it becomes
just an obligation to fulfill the wishes of the guy, that you
would maybe the guy would have to be alive not only when
the משלח Meshaleach died but even when the money was being delivered.
It's true, that's true. Okay, but the גמרא Gemara is using it
as a way to get to a similar result as שכיב מרע.
Shchiv mera. A similar result to the guy being on the deathbed
is that the guy was alive and healthy and then he died
and it becomes a special obligation of מצוה לקיים. Mitzvah lekayeim. So
even because of the special הלכה halacha of a deathbed bequest of
דברי שכיב מרע divrei Shchiv mera or because the guy was healthy
and then died and it's מצוה לקיים, Mitzvah lekayeim, that's what creates
the obligation to deliver the money, but ultimately not הולך. Holeich הולך
לאו כזכי. Holeich lav kizachi. Okay, so the גמרא takes what clearly
seemed to be at least one side of the debate that it
works just because automatically it works. הולך כזכי, Holeich kizachi what we
were assuming, and explained it all into as a special case. Okay.
Yes.
Is it true of all these cases in the case of שכיב
מרע? Shchiv mera? If the guy is שכיב מרע Shchiv mera but
the intended recipient dies before this guy dies? Ah,
right.
So that's a good question, right, but שכיב מרע Shchiv mera because
the שכיב מרע Shchiv mera it sort of takes effect immediately on
condition... you asked a very good question which I don't want to
answer now because it's complicated. But שכיב מרע Shchiv mera you're right,
it's like is it that the words of the שכיב מרע Shchiv
mera take effect immediately on the eventuality that the guy does die,
the guy in his deathbed does die, as opposed to you know
the
because in the case of the שכיב מרע Shchiv mera it said
you know הא דאיתא למקבל בשעת. hadei isa le-mekabel beshaat.
Yeah,
let's just hold off actually, I have to double check some of
that, okay? But you're right, it's a good question to ask by
the שכיב מרע Shchiv mera as well, which is when does the
actual thing take effect. Hold on, let me just check רש״י. Rashi.
One minute. Yeah, I mean רש״י Rashi says
הא דאיתא hadei isa you know בשעת מתנת
ממון, beshaat matnas mamos, רש״י Rashi says ושליח זכה בהן מיד u-shliach
zachah ba-hen mi-yad וכשמת
יורשיו
זוכים מכחו.
u-keshe-meis yorshov
zochim mi-kocho.
Anyway,
yeah, I'll double check on that, but the case is but you're
right that the case of שכיב מרע Shchiv mera you know it
takes assuming the שכיב מרע Shchiv mera dies it takes effect immediately.
All right. So now the גמרא says like this. Where are we?
הוה בבירא... Hava bi-virei...
Okay, so גמרא says like this: לימא הולך כזכי תנאי היא. leima
Holeich kizachi tana'i hi.
You know let's end here because the next ברייתא Braita is going
to be and it's not complicated but you have to a little
bit hold קאפ. kop. I mean so it's just so we'll end
here and we'll pick up tomorrow with this whole issue about הולך
כזכי Holeich kizachi. and the guy who sends something to be delivered
and then the recipient or the משלח Meshaleach dies and whether it
gets delivered or not. So just to remind what we said now
and then we'll pick up here tomorrow: if the guy says go
ahead deliver and then the person he sent it to isn't around,
whether it goes back to the משלח Meshaleach or not, the simple
debate would seem to be is הולך כזכי. Holeich kizachi When he
says deliver it to the guy, does the other side own it
right away or not? And rather than sort of accepting that there's
a debate of הולך Holeich כזכי kizachi and even though we've even
assuming הולך Holeich is כזכי, kizachi, the גמרא gives a whole series
of explanations that הולך is not כזכי and that the reason that
it works is because some scenario of either שכיב מרע Shchiv mera
or מצוה לקיים דברי המת. Mitzvah lekayeim divrei hameis. And that's why
it's working. But a normal scenario of הולך says the גמרא would
not be כזכי, different than what we had been saying before. So
we are going to pick up with this and a ברייתא, Braita,
working through a ברייתא Braita that exactly is about this type of
a case which'll take us to the end of the פרק. perek.
We'll pick up with that.